[Music]
hey hey welcome back
it is day three day three is always an
exciting day in camp
because we put the hardest one on day
three it's just kind of how we do the
do the camp so you you get better and
better and better and so wednesday is
like when you're ready to tackle the
hardest thing
uh and then it'll get easier uh after
that thursday's a little easier
friday's usually kind of like a half day
right so today we're going to tackle
something
uh something big i'm here with my
campers again as per usual
uh campers are you ready to tackle
something huge today
yeah are you ready to go we'll see we'll
see
um i will say that like it is literally
so big you may want to plan
to do this video like part of it now and
then part of it later
because it's it's a big one right it's
good for you though
uh let's uh let's see what we're making
so i've got a demo solution on here
now normally the demo solution i just
kind of show
pretty quickly just for what we're
trying to do
but this time what i want to do is i
want you to think about
what types of things you would have to
write in the code so what are some
things and i'll say some out loud as
we're doing it
um but here's how the game works so when
i hit the play button
uh this game is called irish sheepdog i
am the irish sheepdog so i'm running
around
um and what i'm doing is i'm trying to
push sheep
into the pen and you can see that the
way that i push them is i get behind
them
and then i drive them into the pen
driving the dog around is actually kind
of hard
he uses up arrow to go forwards
and then he turns with left and right
and then he can also go backwards that's
just kind of a feature of the dog
and whenever he's touching the sheep the
sheep
go into the pin one trick you can do
which is kind of fun is backwards you
don't push sheep
so you kind of like back over the top of
them and then you can get in front of
them
you'll you'll learn that it takes a
little while
to get good at driving the sheepdog so
that was a demo now let's talk about
responsibilities so when the game starts
a few things had to happen right so one
thing that had to happen
is somebody has to make all the sheep
right
that's something that has to happen
also the dog has to move with the arrow
keys
uh that's something that has to happen
sheep
um if they're touching the dog they need
to move with the dog
uh sheep that are touching the pin have
to move with the pin
so i have to move into the pin um and
then at the end of the game there's also
this
fastest time so right now last time my
fastest time was 45
i'm going to see if i'm faster this time
not really behind him good so i'll get
behind him good
and there you can see that i got 39
seconds so the idea of this game
is you're trying to crawl them as fast
as you can and it keeps track of your
fastest time
by the way there's also a feature that
if spacebar resets the fastest time
so that's what the game is and our goal
this time
since it is it doesn't necessarily look
big yet but it's big
trust me it's big is to work on planning
so one of the big things for today uh
that we want to do is we want you to be
able to
think about a plan so really when you're
making games on your own you just kind
of come up with ideas
um but what you need to do is you kind
of need to get out a pencil and paper
and just kind of like plan who's going
to be responsible for what
so we're going to do that with our
campers together
so we're going to try to come up with
what are some of the different tasks
that we need to do in this game and then
which sprite
is going to be responsible for it i'm
going to move the camera over to where
you can see this projector better
all right so um obviously these are
slides so i can only like go in
in some order but i'm going to ask my
campers um what are some things that
that need to happen what are some tasks
that need to happen this game
keegan need to create 10 sheep uh that's
a good one so i'm gonna go ahead and go
uh to that one um you got you got one
for free so
i had started timer is something that
needs to happen so we need to create ten
sheep
um these ten sheep are all going to be
clones so i could have written on the
word
clones on here because there's only one
sheep sprite
also i'm going to add one more on here
for what keegan said these sheep
i don't know if you noticed but they're
randomly put on there but in places that
are not touching the pen or the dog
because you don't want to start on the
dog and you definitely don't want to
start in the pen
so that's something that we're going to
do what's another task that we need to
do
mckinley have the dog move with the
arrow keys
have the dog move the arrow keys that's
that's a great one i don't know what's
next
uh oh awesome you you locked right into
it so the dog needs to move using the
arrow keys
um so he's got the up uh the down
uh and then the left and the right so
we're gonna have to do those things
uh what other things have to happen
keegan you need to make a sound you need
to make a sound so like whenever the
sheep
uh get put into the pen you have to make
a sound that's a little lower on my list
someone asked mckinley for one
mckimley what's another thing you have
to do um
whenever you're touching the sheet in
the back
you can move them okay so what she said
was she said
um when you're touching a sheep with the
dog they have to also move right so
sheep touching the dog will move with
the dog
and then the one keegan said was
basically sheep touching the pen
are moved into the pen right so there's
there's a couple things that have to
happen there
um other things that have to happen i'll
just kind of throw these last couple you
guys did great thank you very much
um we're gonna have to track the number
of sheep that are in the pin
um and then we're gonna have to like
know when the game ends
and then you can't see this but there's
some like game over like check
for the fastest time now the next
question who's responsible for these
things
now obviously we've got a dog
we've got a sheep uh we've got a pen
um and then we've also got the
background or the stage
and so those are the the three sprites
that we're gonna have
and then you've also always got the
background so who's going to start the
timer so who do you think is going to
reset the timer
keegan yeah so you can actually do this
on either it could be done by the
backdrop
or you could do it with the dog uh
either would work
who's going to create the 10 sheep
mckinley the backdrop
the backdrop yep and now i'm gonna i'm
gonna cheat a little bit
this game is pretty big i'm gonna
choose this is a voluntary choice to
um do these things that could happen on
the backdrop
i'm going to choose to do them on the
dog just so that i have no code on the
backdrop
that may not be the greatest choice in
the world but that's how i'm going to do
it and you're stuck
with the way i do things right so we're
going to choose to just do them on the
dog
and then this creation of the sheep that
aren't touching the pen
this is going to be the job of the sheep
by the way the sheep are actually going
to be involved with the creation of
sheep as well right because they have to
have a little bit of code
dog moves with the arrow key who does
that dog
dog so that one's right um the sheep
will move with the dog who does that
that's actually a combo so it's a it's a
dog and the sheep combo right
sheep touching the pen moved into the
pen
that's the sheep and then it also
involves the pen right
uh and then there's some um tracking of
the sheep in the pen who do you think's
gonna do that though
yeah so the pen plus the sheep
um and then the game over stuff i'm just
gonna all do with the dog
um so this is my this is my plan
i could say that with the slides a
little cleaner
uh so i mean i think that maybe it looks
cleaner on the slides
i always like this game but you cover up
your whiteboard uh with this
so each of these responsibilities uh is
going to happen
by one of our sprites right and then if
i were to take this list
uh and rearrange it by by whose
responsibilities
everything was there's certain
responsibilities for the sheep
so this is what the sheep needs to do uh
there's certain responsibilities
uh for the pen um and then there's
certain responsibilities for the dog
so it's gonna be kind of complex i'm
gonna move the camera back over
uh and so we'll actually refer to this
plan uh as we build our game
um and we're gonna start somewhere uh
we're actually gonna start
with um i'm gonna give you some some
images uh here in just a second
and we're gonna start by implementing
things on the dog
now the dog actually i'll say has a
couple things he's got
kind of some initialization things that
happen uh and then he's got some
movement things that happen
and then he's got some game over things
that happen those three categories
we're actually going to break down for
the dog so to get started with this what
i need you to do
is i need you to remix
a scratch project that i made for you
the link
that you need to go to is is right here
so it's scratch.mit.edu projects and
then you can see this is the number
i'll put this number in the email
i'll put this number in the video just
below
this youtube video also put this number
on the main camp page so
connectingwithcode.org
camp if all those things failed you can
always type it
and essentially what you need to do is
you need to go to this webpage so here
i'm on this webpage
and then you need to click on the word
remix so if you click on the word remix
it will actually make a copy of this
project and put it over in your area
and it will name it irish sheepdog
starting code remix
what i'm going to choose to do is i'm
going to take off the word starting code
remix
because this is my irish sheepdog
so that's what i'm going to save this
project as all right so whenever i get
starting code
from someone i always like to take a
minute and see
what all is there right what am i
looking at so you can see that i've got
a couple different sprites i've got a
sheep sprite
so here's my sheep i've got a sheep dog
sprite
and then i've got a pen and also i've
got a backdrop
by the way these are all just kind of
custom images which is why it was easier
to remix than to let you find these
things
if you go look at the costumes you can
see there's only one costume for the
sheep that's pretty simple
the dog was actually an animated gif so
he actually has
um literally like 141 costumes
and it'll make him look like he's
barking so it's an animated gif file
and then the pen i did something super
sneaky for the pen
the pen actually is a costume
that has various sheep in it right so
it's kind of funny costume one has zero
sheep
costume two has one sheep custom three
has two sheep
and so actually what we're gonna do is
whenever they uh get put
into the pin really we're gonna delete
the clone
and we're gonna switch the costume on
the pen sneaky isn't it
yeah very sneaky all right so uh let's
let's dive in and start coding we're
going to start in uh with the dog
and so the dog some
initialized tasks he's got some movement
tasks
and then he's got some like check for
game over task
and one thing you can do when you're
planning your code is you can use
functions
just to organize complex things so what
we're going to do is we're going to make
these three functions initialize
move and check for game over and you can
see that this is what the dog does he
initializes once
and then he forever moves and checks her
game over so let's go ahead
and go into the code for the dog
let's grab a win green flag clicked
and then to keep ourselves organized
because we've got a big game here we're
going to use
functions i have to stay organized the
first function is going to be called
initialize i'm going to go and type the
whole the whole thing here
so you create the function initialize uh
and then we'll stick on the initialize
block
initialize is of course hard to spell i
think i got it right i had to go help
keegan
after initialize i also want to make a
block called move
and so move is going to happen inside a
forever loop
so i'm going to go ahead and go to
control and say forever
and then i'm going to stick on my move
block in there
and then the last function we're going
to use is
check for game over
of a long one to type there so check for
game over by the way if you ever need to
pause the video because it takes you
longer to type than it takes me to type
that's totally fine just pause the video
no big deal
and we've got these these three
functions check for game over
so the code so far doesn't do anything
it's simply
getting some planning together i'm gonna
do check for game over last so i'm just
gonna kind of like set it over here out
of the way
but this initialize and move we're going
to do pretty early
so what are some things that the dog
needs to do
during the initialize thing and this is
where plans are really useful
he needs to start a timer
all right so so part of this is he needs
to start a timer
there's also some things that i realize
now should have been in my plan that
weren't there
and that's fine i just add them for
example
i never said in my plan that i should
set the dog's starting position
well i would like for him to start i'm
just going to make him start in the
corner
um there's a good spot that he can kind
of start over here and that wasn't in my
plan but i've got to do it
so i'm actually going to put him where i
want him to start and then i'm going to
go to motion and i'm going to say
go to xy that's going to be part of
initialize
and then i'm going to go ahead and also
put on this point in direction 90. so he
points in direction 90.
so just to make sure that my code's
working if i put him somewhere different
when i hit the green flag he should snap
to that starting position
so um the code doesn't do much yet but
it does work
it's kind of nice that you can just make
these dummy functions
it's just kind of like placeholders for
your planning but we haven't actually
used them yet
all right so the thing that it's said to
do is start a timer there's actually a
built-in timer
it's in sensing and so the timer is
actually like a magical built-in thing
and so the only thing we need to do uh
to start the timer
is we need this function reset timer
so that's literally the only thing we
need to do i'll make my screen just a
little bigger for you here
uh so reset timer uh we'll we'll do that
task
and so like if i was marking them off i
would just mark that line off that one's
done
uh the next thing i need to do is i need
to create 10 sheep
so i'm going to use cloning to my
advantage here
so i'm going to go to uh control and
make a loop
that goes 10 times obviously we could
put 10 of them in a row but we just want
a loop
that does it and what i want to do is i
want to
create a clone of sheep
if i were to run this now it would look
like nothing happened so if i run it now
it it worked it created 10 sheep
the original is still there so there's
actually 11 sheep
uh if i were to move them all out there
should be 11 sheep in there
so obviously it worked but it wasn't
what i wanted to have happen right
so what i want to happen is i want to
create 10 sheep but i want the sheep to
go to random positions
that responsibility is actually not
on the dog that responsibility
is going to be on the the sheep right so
not touching the pen or the dog so
they're going to be in a random position
uh
not touching the sheep of the dog so go
into the sheep
we're going to be bouncing around
sprites for a long time so just kind of
expect that we're just kind of like
we're in the dog for a second we're in
the sheep for a second we're in the pen
for a second you get the idea
in the sheep so the sheep need
when i start as cloned so sheep
start as clone the first thing that you
want sheep to do
is you want them to show up because
we're going to hide the original we've
done this trick a few times
so i want them to show up and i want
them to be in a random position
so i'm going to go to motion
and say go to random position
now if i start the game again it goes
much better
if you were to actually count the sheep
there would be 11 of them
because we haven't hidden the original
yet so i'm going to
stop the game i'm going to find the
original and i'm going to hide the
original
and so now when i run it there should
actually be 10 sheep
now the next thing i want to do is i
want to point out a problem
oh the mine's a perfect example notice
where one of my sheep randomly started
i had a sheep that randomly started
right in the pen
right um and that we could make that
work but that's not what i want to do
because i don't want to start with them
in the pen
likewise they might randomly start on
top of the dog
right that's not terrible but it's not
what i want
so i want to make sure that they don't
start on the dog
and that they don't start on the pen so
how do we do that
uh do you guys have any ideas if
statements
all right so mckinley said if statements
if statements uh would totally work
um but the thing is if we put an if
statement in here
it would check it once right so like we
could say if
uh you're on the pen or on the dog then
go to a new random position
uh mckinley you got an idea
yeah so an if statement in a forever
loop now
we don't want to go forever though
because we want to just keep picking new
random positions until
we're somewhere not touching the dog
does that make sense yeah
so yeah so there's a lot of good a lot
of good options i love that you guys are
just firing things out
we're going to use repeat and tell
so here's what we're going to do we're
going to
pick a random position and then we're
repeat until we're not touching
the dog and we're not touching the pin
if we are if either of those things are
true then we're going to pick a new
random position
and then we'll check again right so
we're going to pick a random position
maybe it's fine if it's not we're gonna
pick a new one
until this condition is true now what
makes this hard is this condition
so it has to be not touching the dog
or the pen so how do we write uh this
this statement so we're going to repeat
until it's going to be complex
so one thing we're going to do is we're
going to have in here
a touching uh the dog
and a touching uh the pen
now we want to go and tell we're not
touching those things
so operators have knots so
not touching the sheep dog
not touching the pen so i want to repeat
until
i'm not touching him and i'm not
touching him right
so there's an and statement in here so
this thing
it's subtle but it gets really big
really quick right now you have to be
careful when you drag these things in
make sure you grab it like from the knot
um and so this is like
the biggest if statement ever right um
it's so big that i can't even like see
the whole thing so repeat until
i'm not touching the sheepdog and
i'm not touching the pen it's actually
quite readable
the hardest part is actually like
getting it situated to where it goes in
here
remember that you like put the tip of it
in there and it goes white
so we test your uh your code dexterity
skills there
um to see if you can make that line of
code so you can see that this time
a sheep started right on me but now with
my new revised
code uh it should not happen it looks
like it happened
why did it happen um must have goofed
something up
they started the pen so i goofed
all right so what did i do wrong i
actually i noticed what i did wrong uh
almost right away
my show is at the bottom the problem
with having show at the bottom is it's
invisible right there's no way to be
touching something when you're invisible
so you actually need the show this time
to be at the top
technically it could be here or here it
doesn't really matter
i'll put it put it right here just to
prove that i understand how it works
so now when you run it they never show
up whoa he's
he showed up above the dog just barely
snuck in there right
another thing that mckinley did is she
added another and statement
and another sensor and she added a
um and not oh i should have done it the
way mckinley did it
and not touching edge as well
right so if you want to throw this in
you can because you'll notice that right
now they can show up like
half off the screen i think that seems
like a good thing to add
it makes it even more complicated right
so
i'm going to stick this whole and
i don't care if you do this or not this
is optional if you've got this working
feel free to move forwards if you want
to use sissy's fancy thing
she took this whole and and dropped it
into right there
and now she made a oh shoot i messed up
so now she grabbed a mega thing so i've
got to grab the right word and to move
it around
um and then there it is i told you it
was a hard day
i didn't uh i didn't hide that fact at
all maybe i'll get to where i can show
you more code
but now i've got sissy's solution so i'm
not touching the sheepdog
and not touching the pen and
not touching the edge um pretty easy to
read and review it's just hard to make
right so now let's see if sissy's
solution works so now i should never be
on the edge as well [ __ ] i love it good
call
all right so we are uh doing things uh
great we're knocking things off of our
list that's super
next what we probably ought to do is we
ought to
move the dog using the arrow keys i went
one slide too far
so initialization is in good shape
moving the dog using the arrow keys is
next
so i'm going to go back to the dogs code
so the dog's initialize is in is in
pretty good shape
uh i'm i'm okay with what's going on
there now i'm going to go over to the
dog's move area
the dog's move area is going to move
using
four different keys um up down left and
right
this does not need to be in a forever
loop because
over here we've already got a forever
loop right so we we just we just have if
statements over here
and so he's going to respond to the four
different keys so i'm going to have
a key for up down left and right so i'm
going to drag them all in
and then i'm going gonna switch them to
up
down left
uh and right uh and i'm gonna give my
campers just a minute to catch up
all right so let's move uh let's do the
movement with the arrow keys
so up arrow is going to move the dog
forward uh so we're going to move at
some speed
so i'm going to drag this move 10 in
there i could type in a number
for his speed that'd be fine but again
it's kind of like ground level in the
last app it's a variable that we're
going to use in various places
so i'm going to actually make a variable
called dog speed
i'm going to set it in initials and
initialize
so go to variables click on make a
variable
we want this to be available for all
sprites because we want the sheep to
know the dog speed as well
i'm going to type it like this i'm going
to type dog speed
again that's just how i like to do
variables so it's two words
it's smooshed together it's called camel
case so i've got dog speed
so i make the variable first the next
thing i want to do is i want to set the
variable
i don't care where you set it and
initialize it does not matter at all
i'm going to set it right at the top i'm
going to set my dog speed to 3.
i like doing this because if you use
this variable in multiple places and you
decide to change it you're going to
only need to change it right here it's a
really great way to do code
and so over here i'm going to move at
dog speed
by the way i don't really need to show
it on the screen so i'm just going to
hide it
so it's not visible there but what up
arrow is going to do is going to move at
dog speed so you can actually play your
game now
and when you hit up arrow your dog
should move at dog speed
and if you want him faster you can make
him faster but three is good enough
down arrow is going to move in the
negative direction
so i'm going to go into motion i'm going
to say move
and then he's going to move in negative
dog speed
now this one i don't care if you want to
just type in negative 3 i'm ok with that
but if you wanted to actually do it like
the elegant way you would use
multiplication um and you would use
the variable dog speed again and you
move it
negative one times dog speed right
so that's like the elegant way to do it
because you actually get to use your
variable again
so now i can go forwards uh with up
arrow uh and then i can go backwards
with down arrow
because he's moving at negative dog
speed right
kind of fun uh left and right arrows
are going to be turns so let's go ahead
and figure out which is which so
turning left is this one because that's
going to be kind of like a
left turn i'm going to be a little lazy
i'm just going to type a 5 in here and
then the other one
is going to be a 5 there again if i was
like trying to be really elegant with my
code i'd make a variable for that as
well
but i think that i'm going to cheat a
little bit here because this app
is is quite long so now i go forwards
and backwards
and then i can also go right uh and left
and take a minute and just kind of
practice with your dog right because you
need to be able to like drive them into
the pen
and then what i typically do is i back
up and then i like drive these guys into
the pen
um and then i kind of back up behind
them and then drive one and getting good
at your own game is fun
because then you'll be able to get the
fastest time so driving things
into the pen so i'm pretty happy with
the dog movements
so i would call that a check mark on
that
so dog moves using arrow keys is done
next thing we want to do is we want the
sheep
that are touching the dog to move with
the dog
this is is a little sneaky as well so
the sheep have to move with me
so we've never done anything like this
in a game before how do we do that so
essentially right here the dog moved
right so he moved at 10 steps
and what he really needs to do is he
needs to tell everybody else
that he's moving and then if they want
to move
with him they need to know two things
they need to know how fast he's going
and they need to know what direction
he's pointing in um so here's what we're
going to do
we're going to make a variable so go to
variables
we're going to call it dog direction
because the idea is is that these other
sheep if they're going to move with the
dog they've got to know his speed
which is already a global variable and
they also need to know his direction so
go ahead and save off dog direction
so what he's going to do is when he
moves
he's going to set
the variable called dog direction so
he's going to set dog direction
and inside motion there's actually a
variable already called direction
so he's going to set this global
variable that everybody can see
called dog direction to his direction so
now everybody knows
how fast he's going and what direction
he's pointing in
and then he's going to broadcast an
event
so he's going to so it's in events
broadcast
and the name of this message it could be
anything you want i'm just going to call
it
dog moved so the dog moved
so he's just telling everybody hey the
dog moved
um and then it'll be their job to see if
they also should move
right um and so he's broadcasting dog
move to
everybody and it's the sheep that are
gonna have to listen
right so let's come over to the sheep
um and this was part of our plan right
so we said that um
that the sheep uh we're gonna have to
move with the dog that was something
that we planned
so come in here to sheep and for the
sheep say
when i receive so find when i receive
so when i receive dog moved i have to
decide
if i should move too so campers i get
your opinion
how are how are the sheep gonna know if
they should move
if they're touching the dog if they're
touching the dog that's exactly right so
i'm gonna go into control and if
i am touching
the dog so if he moved and i'm touching
him
then i should move too and so what i
should do
is i should um point
in the same direction as the dog so i
should point myself in the dog's
direction
by the way i don't need to display that
on the screen so i can i can get rid of
that
i just hit the check mark here to not
display it
so i need to point in the direction of
the dog and i need to move
um at the speed of the dog
so dog speed and it will appear
visually like he's pushing me but really
i'm just traveling at the same speed as
him
and at the same direction as him let's
try it
and see if this works so now every time
i move i broadcast that i'm moving
but if they're not touching me then
nothing happens but if i start touching
this one
you can see how they snap to the same
direction so as soon as i touch this one
it snaps to the same direction
and it appears as though i'm moving them
which is cool
and so i'm going to push them to the
sheep push them to the pin when they get
to the pin nothing happens
notice that i can back right over them
and nothing big happens
and then i can push them in and this is
where kind of like backing up
makes you better at your game you'll
also notice that if you look at the code
it doesn't care if you're actually
behind them so this is kind of funny i'm
just going to put my tail on this guy
my tail is enough to make him come with
me right
um cool so this is going really well
i'm going to pause and help my campers
for a little bit um
all right so things are going really
good by the way this is a great time to
take a break
um our family we decided to just take a
little break we we jumped and touched
the ceiling for a little while we ate
some snacks
pause it take a little break good time
to take a break um hey i did notice one
thing i noticed that my dog
um he isn't going through different
costumes that's actually something i
meant to do earlier
let's fix this real quick go into the
dogs code
and go find his like main event loop
over here
and inside here uh just grab a
um next costume command uh where is it
at i always have trouble finding this
next costume
and just stick it you can honestly you
can stick it anywhere in this loop
i'm going to stick it right there it
doesn't really matter that way it just
kind of makes a cool pyramid
and so now you can see like as soon as i
stick it in there the dog starts uh
starts barking by the way when i first
made this game i
actually made a bark sound the whole
time it gets really annoying
right so if he just sits there and he
just barks the whole time you're just
like dog stop barking
all right so overall very happy with the
game i'd say it seems pretty obvious
what needs to happen next uh what
campers what do you guys think we should
do next
have the sheep actually go into the pen
have the sheep
have the sheep actually like go into the
pen that seems like a good thing
um and that's hopefully what our plan is
telling us to do next so
uh sheep touching the dog will move so
we did that one
and then our plan says the next thing is
sheep touching the pin
are moved into the pin um and we need to
track the number of sheep that are in
the pin
right so that's our next task so we
decided that responsibility would be on
the sheep so the sheep would do that
so let's go into the sheep's code
and so the sheep needs to check
if they're in the pen we could put that
code down here because this is where
they move so we could put it down here
or we could put it up here it honestly
doesn't matter
i'm going to choose to put it
as a forever loop up here just because
that's how i typically write code and
that
like there's something that you're doing
forever so i'm going to go into control
and i'm going to stick a forever loop um
on the bottom
of this when i start as clone script
so he's going to like go to some
position and then he's going to forever
check if he's touching the pin or not
so that's of course an if statement and
touching the pin is a sensing so
forever if i'm touching
uh the pen so the sheet pen then i'm
going to do the code that's inside of
here
the code that i want to do is i want to
increment a counter
so that we know how many sheep there are
and then i also want
to change the pin so that it looks like
i'm in there
and then i want to delete the clone so a
lot of things i need to do
let's do the variable first so click on
variables
let's make a variable we might
display this variable so i'm going to
use the
the naming convention that i use when
something is displayed
i make it public because i'm going to
display it and i'm going to call it num
sheep whenever you make a variable
you need to initialize its value
somewhere um
and the question of where do i
initialize the value
um that could be anywhere normally i'd
put something like that on the stage
this time i'm not using stage code so
i'm going to put it on the dog so the
dog already has like an initialized area
that seems like a good place to
initialize
uh num sheep uh to be zero as well so
this is like
number of sheep in the pen right if you
want to be very verbose about it
so i initialize it there so you make it
you initialize it
um and then you increment it over on the
sheep
again notice how i just seamlessly hop
back and forth from the sheep to the dog
so i'm going to change it in here so i'm
going to change
my num sheet so change num sheet by one
so that's an important thing i have to
do the next thing i have to do
is i need to um play a sound because we
always play sounds
let's go ahead and play i kind of like
pop because it's like i pop
into the pen so
code sound
play sound pop i'll go ahead and play it
until it's done
because i'm going to delete myself at
the end of this i want to make sure that
it plays
i also need to tell the pin to update
right so i'm going to need to tell the
pen to update whenever you communicate
from one sprite to another
uh campers what are we going to need to
do to communicate from one sprite to
another
broadcast we have to broadcast an event
um so he's going to
broadcast an event
i'm i'm gonna have to make a new event
name so a new message
i'm gonna call this one update pin
so i'm gonna broadcast that the pin
image needs to be updated
so update pin
um and then after i tell the pin to
update
i'm going to delete myself so i'm going
to come down
and control it's the bottom command
delete this clone
and so with code you want to do things
sequentially and you want to think about
what needs to happen
and then you've got to execute your plan
so i'm going to change the number of
sheet by one because i'm now in the pen
i'm going to play a sound because sounds
are fun i'm going to tell the pin hey
update pin and then i'm going to delete
this clone
so let's go ahead and go into the pen
and let's respond to
update pen so i'm in the pen now
in the pen i need to go to events
say when i receive
so when the pen receives update pen
he's going to use the variable num sheep
to set
his costume so looks
switch to costume
now the question is how do you switch to
the correct costume
right so it's going to somehow have to
be
based on uh num sheep right
and so let's look at his costumes so his
costumes have names they also have
numbers
so i could set this by saying costume
one
or the name which is called sheep zero
this is costume number two and its name
is sheep one
so there's kind of a weird off by one
here right so um
when the sheep is zero i want to use
costume one when the sheep is one
i want to use costume two so it's kind
of off by one there right
so um i'll ask my campers if i were to
put this in here it would work out badly
because it's kind of gotten off by one
so what do i need to do campers have you
figured this out
um number is sheep minus one yeah so
there's a a statement that it's
number sheep minus one um it's actually
not minus it's plus yeah yeah that makes
sense um
so i want uh plus so
number of sheep so my costume is equal
to the number of sheep so right now it's
num sheep is zero so i want costume one
does that make sense
and so as the number of sheep increases
um my costume is gonna gonna get better
and better and it'll look like
uh the sheep are going into the pen
right because the sheep
the clone itself is gonna get deleted uh
let's see if it works
so now i um i run i've got a couple
sheep here that are going in
so overall that was going good
one thing that was broken about my game
is when i started it it looked like
there was sheep in there it's like when
i started it
um it looked like there were sheep in
there that's a mistake and the reason it
did that
is because um i never reset
it to be empty does that make sense
so a task that i never predicted
was necessary i realized that i need to
do now i need to call
update pen when the game first starts
i'm going to do that from the dog so
this is a task that i
did not see coming which was fine i
didn't plan for this
i just know that i need to do it now so
i need to
um inside my initialize area i need to
broadcast
uh update pen and that way like see how
there's a bunch of people in there right
now
that way when the game starts it's going
to update the pen
uh to clear them all out in fact it
would probably look better if i did that
like really early right
so i set the number of sheep to zero and
then i
broadcast update pen then i do the rest
of the stuff
that way even if i um start with
a bunch of sheep in there when my game
starts
they'll they'll be gone by the way it
looks like my original sheep is uh still
on the screen here
um i'm gonna go back and hide my
original sheep i don't know
i don't know how he got unhidden uh but
i want my original uh to be hidden
until i'm going to move him way over in
the corner uh and hide him there
mckinley you got a statement so she has
a theory about how it happened and
uh that that probably writes this but
now i can put
sheep in here and it looks like they go
into the pen which is cool um and then
eventually i'll get the the final sheep
in there
um and then um nothing happens right
so our game is going really really good
we've got the sheep touching the pen are
moved in tracking the number of people
moved in
the only thing i need to do now is the
what's called the in-game stuff so i
need to
make sure i've started my timer which
we've already done that and then once
all the sheep are in the pin
the game ends and i check for fastest
time
let's go look to see what what the
solution did on this
so you can see that there was this
variable fastest time
um and the idea was is that it would
track how long it took you to get all
the sheep in
uh so i'll just go ahead and get them
all in again here
um all right so i paused it there just
so you didn't have to watch me collect
sheep
um but i'm about to push the final two
sheep in and then i'm going to let you
see this is the solution what should
happen
and so what should happen is it should
bark a few times
it should say a message about how long
it took you
and then if it was the fastest time then
it should update the fastest time so
there's a lot of details going on there
so let's go ahead and see
if we can do some of those things so
when all the sheep are in the pen the
game ends
our plan is that that's going to be a
responsibility of the dog
so let's go into the dogs code
and a function we have never used is
actually this check for game over so now
we're going to focus on
a check for game over so what check for
game over needs to do
is it needs to check to see if num sheep
is 10.
maybe i zoomed in too much there so i
need to check
if my number of sheep is equal to
10 so i need an operator for equals
i need a num sheep
is equal to 10. so if that
happens then i need to start my game
over
sequence right so my game over sequence
has to do a couple of things
it has to um say a message
so let's just go ahead and go into looks
i'm going to choose to have him think it
right
um and so i'm going to have him think
like you win
is how i'm going to start to test this
i could play the whole game it becomes
very
tedious to test the whole game because
you have to actually get to 10 sheep
so here's what i'm gonna do to make
testing easier
i'm gonna temporarily set this to one
now whenever you do temporary testing
like that you've got to remember to put
it back later
right but now you can see that we can
test this much faster
because we just have to get one sheep in
and then it'll it'll save my message now
what i want my message to say
is i want my message to be more complex
i wanted to say you collected
all the sheep
in some number of seconds right
it turns out that you you can't put the
variable right into the sentence here
unless you use this thing called a
a join operator so here's what i'm going
to do i'm actually going to like
slowly join this together so i'm going
to say you collected all the sheep in
and then it's going to say like some
number of seconds
and so what i want to do here uh keegan
i'll help you type this don't worry
i'm going to grab the timer the timer is
in sensing
so timer is right here so you collected
all the sheep
in this many seconds
can you see how i built that up so i i
started off with
this thing you collected all the sheep
in timer
and then on this one down here it says
apple seconds but where it currently
says apple i'm going to drop this other
one
so i'm going to say you collected all
the sheep in
blank seconds and then to make sure that
there's spaces i'm going to make sure
that there's a space after the word in
just to make sure that there's a space
there and then i'm going to make sure
that there's a space
before the word seconds right so there's
actually kind of like a space there
and so i'm going to stick that in here
and so i'm going to say go so now when i
get one sheep
in it says you collected all the sheep
in four point blah blah blah seconds um
and notice that
the game keeps playing uh well the the
game keeps playing that's fine
um i'm gonna stick on a stop all
at the bottom here so now the game won't
keep playing
but as soon as i get one sheep in it'll
say you collected all the sheep in 4.5
seconds
that's just a little faster than i can
read so i'm going to bump the message up
to like four seconds
and you can see how useful it is uh to
do
fast testing you collected all the sheep
in 4.18 seconds
great i'm going to help keegan type this
all right so we are doing super good the
only thing i want to add is i want to
keep track of the fastest time to make
it like a game right
so let's go to variables make a variable
make the variable called fastest time
for all sprites you can see that i'm
planning on showing this
so i use my like show it on the screen
format
by the way num sheep i don't think i
really need to show that so i'm gonna
hide numb sheep
um and fastest time i'm gonna actually
put it up in this corner just because uh
this corner is where my dog starts right
um cool so let's go ahead and
have a cheat to where we can reset it so
here's what i want to do
if you press the space bar then
set fastest time
to 999 999
so um we made the variable and then the
way we initialize it is kind of a funny
system
um you press the space bar and it'll
just set it to 999. so that way it kind
of like resets the fastest time so it
resets the high scores board so now what
we want to do
is inside this check for game over i
want to see if this is the fastest time
so really what i want to do is i want an
if statement so i'm going to go to
control
and i'm going to set it down here
because i'm going to do like a little
planning first
so i'm going to say if
something is less than something else my
campers told me i was going too fast so
i'll pause for just a minute here
um so um so we made this variable
fastest time
we made this win space key press set it
to 999.
um and now we're kind of like building
up an if statement over here so this is
eventually going to get in my code but
right now it's over here so i'm going to
say if
my current time is less than the
previous fastest
so i'm going to on the right hand side
it's going to be like so if my current
time
is less than fastest the current time by
the way is a variable that's in sensing
so i'm going to come down to um sensing
and so it's the timer
that's what it's called so if the timer
is less than fastest time um and then
i'm gonna
set fastest time if that happens so
set fastest time
equal to uh the timer
so i had to kind of like jump back and
forth uh quite a bit there
but i think the concept is pretty clear
so like if the timer is less than
fastest time
then set fastest time to timer
and i want to stick this if statement
just above
uh where it does the thinking i chose to
put it above the thinking because i
don't want that thinking
to like hurt my fastest time right
um oops it looks like it's kind of
blurred there
um so i could test that but i'm gonna do
one more thing uh really quick
um i'm gonna choose to to bark a couple
times
um there's a sound that's built in uh
called bark uh it's actually already
here on the dog
and i'm going to choose to bark four
times so to bark four times
i'm gonna grab a repeat four
and in sound i'm going to play sound
bark until done four times
um and that'll be like the last uh thing
that i do
right so i'm gonna think that thought
for a little while
uh and then i'm gonna bark some uh and
then the game will be over
you could choose to bark first you could
choose to do them at the same time
there's lots of ways you could do it i'm
currently at num1
but i want to try it at num1 just to see
if it works
so i'm going to slowly win the game so i
slowly won the game
so that took 7.342 seconds
and then the machine gun barking that's
fine now i'm going to
quickly win the game so you can see
right now it's 7.4 seconds but if i
quickly win the game
um oops i caught too many sheep
hold on i need to catch only one jeep
kind of a bad test
um does this look like one sheep to you
keegan
uh yeah that didn't work either all
right i can do this
i've got to catch exactly one sheep uh
so let's try to catch exactly one sheep
for my test
um so 6.17 seconds i
work and then my machine gun bark
by the way if you if you don't like how
that worked you could bark
um at the same time um as you think
things
i don't know if i would recommend this
but but you could change it
so i i switched it right so i switched
it to where it's going to like
bark first and then it's going to think
at the same time it's barking
don't care if you change that or not
whichever you want last thing i want to
do is put this back to 10
and i should have a finished game i'm
going to play it one time
see if it works and so i'm going to go
ahead and put my sheep in the pin here
my fastest time by the way is currently
6.1 seconds
i'm just going to hit the space bar to
reset it
and now as soon as i get these guys in
then i've got my
new record so 17.3 not bad
i was going to try to beat it just one
time so i think that i can beat 17
seconds
so i'm going to get them all in i find a
good trick is to go backwards with the
dog and if you want to be really fast
don't even get all the way behind them
just get like on them and that's
actually enough for the dog
i got 15.7 seconds uh so i
i'm a winner uh once i finish my game
what i like to do is i like to share it
um and i like to add some instructions
so use the sheep dog
to put your sheep in the pen with
up down left and
right arrows cool
and then i could tell how to reset the
high score but i won't
now i've got a url that i could send to
uh to grandparents
to friends to family and things like
that um
i suppose i should check in on my
campers to see to see how they're doing
so campers let's see how you did all
right so keegan you're gonna show yours
first
um this game uh has a little bit less
originality uh but go ahead and um
hope keegan's ready to score his last
sheep um and it looks like he
uh collected them all in 37 seconds
which is his fastest time
since did you get yours working
[Music]
so i made her wait with only one sheep
left too because it takes a while
her fastest time is 70 seconds uh and
this one because i made her weight
is going to be worse but i just want to
see if it works so it says yep
you collected them all um and it was in
115 seconds
uh great so you guys can keep playing uh
to see if you can collect them even
faster
did you guys have fun with the hardest
project of the whole week yes
cool i'm glad you liked it i think this
is a fun one i'm sorry it doesn't allow
for more uh creativity
uh but we kind of have to like focus it
just to uh just to be able to do this
whole thing
uh so the summary of this um is really
just
coding is fun i need to update the slide
and we learned a lot of cool skills uh
about planning how do you tackle uh big
projects
and how do you assign responsibilities
we also learned a lot
of cool tricks about like communication
between sprites
uh and having the dog move the sheep
into the pen
whew that was a big one very impressed
pat yourself on the back if you finished
today
you are over the hump and we will see
you again tomorrow
[Music]
bye